<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves out of East India of the cruell and bloody vsage of our English merchants and others at Amboyna, by the Netherlandish gouernour and councell there. To the tune of Braggendary.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19054</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 547</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117782</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852992</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852992</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18350</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19054)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18350)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1193:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves out of East India of the cruell and bloody vsage of our English merchants and others at Amboyna, by the Netherlandish gouernour and councell there. To the tune of Braggendary.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For F. Coules, dwelling at the vpper end of the Old-Baily,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1624]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printed on the verso of STC 353.5. At the end of the ballad is mentioned STC 7451, "You may read more of this bloody tragedy in a booke printed by authory. [sic] 1624".</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>A ballad.</note>
                  <note>Verse - "From India land such newes I haue,".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nederlandsche Oost-Indische Compagnie --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ambon (Indonesia) --  History --  Massacre, 1624 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:18350:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Newes out of Eaſt India: Of the cruell and bloody vſage of our Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chants and others at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> by the Netherlandiſh Gouernour and Councell there.</head>
            <opener>To the tune of Braggendary.</opener>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of scenes of torture and execution: a half-naked man hanging stretched in an X on a door frame, his face bound, while a man on a stool pours water over his head and another man tickles him under the arm with feathers; a second half-naked man kneeling in prayer with his hands bound while another man stands behind him with a drawn sword raised to strike; a third half-naked man sitting on the ground</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>FRom <hi>India</hi> Land ſuch newes I haue,</l>
               <l>of death and deadly dole,</l>
               <l>As may inforce a déepe remorſe,</l>
               <l>to each good Chriſtian ſoule.</l>
               <l>To thinke what Engliſh blood was ſhed,</l>
               <l>Vpon a ſmall occaſion bred.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh heauen looke downe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>vpon poore innocent ſoules.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Betwéene the Engliſh and the Dutch,</l>
               <l>hath béene a long debate:</l>
               <l>And miſchiefes many hath béene wrought,</l>
               <l>againſt our Merchants ſtate,</l>
               <l>Where Merchant-men haue loſt their liues,</l>
               <l>Their goods, their children, and their wiues:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh heauen looke downe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>vpon poore innocent ſoules.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A towne there ſtands <hi>Amboyna</hi> call'd.</l>
               <l>a Caſtle in the ſame;</l>
               <l>Made rich by theſe Low-Country States,</l>
               <l>and Merchants of great name:</l>
               <l>Who on a time a plot deuiz'd,</l>
               <l>To haue our Engliſhmen ſurpriz'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh heauen looke downe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They gaue out words our Engliſhmen,</l>
               <l>by ſecret treaſon wrought,</l>
               <l>The towne and Caſtle to blow vp,</l>
               <l>and ſo in queſtion brought,</l>
               <l>Our Engliſh Merchants dwelling there,</l>
               <l>With all that held our Country deare.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh heauen looke downe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their Gouernor a Councell cal'd,</l>
               <l>and yet no reaſon why,</l>
               <l>That twenty of our Engliſhmen</l>
               <l>ſhould there their cauſes try:</l>
               <l>Aad anſwer for a thing not done,</l>
               <l>Nor any way there thought vpon.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh heauen looke downe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To cruell tortures day by day,</l>
               <l>our Engliſh thus were brought:</l>
               <l>Where ſtrange tormenting inſtruments</l>
               <l>vpon their bodies wrought:</l>
               <l>To make them all confeſſe and ſay,</l>
               <l>They ſought <hi>Amboyna</hi> to betray.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh heauen looke downe, &amp;.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The firſt they laid vpon a Racke,</l>
               <l>with armes and legs abroad,</l>
               <l>And ſpred him, till he did confeſſe</l>
               <l>and moſt vntruly ſhow'd,</l>
               <l>How that our Engliſhmen conſpir'd,</l>
               <l>To haue the town and caſtle fier'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh heauen looke downe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>vpon poore innocent ſoules.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18350:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The ſecond Part,</head>
               <opener>To the ſame tune.</opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe ſecond of theſe wofull men,</l>
                  <l>they bound vnto a ſtake:</l>
                  <l>And throtle him about the necke,</l>
                  <l>till he could hardly ſpeake.</l>
                  <l>Which cruell torments to auoyd,</l>
                  <l>Said that the towne ſhould be deſtroyd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh heauen looke downe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The third they bound in Iron chaines,</l>
                  <l>which griped him ſo ſore,</l>
                  <l>That all his body round about,</l>
                  <l>did guſh out bloody gore:</l>
                  <l>From which to find ſome eaſe he ſayd,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amboyna</hi> ſhould haue béene betrayd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh heauen looke downe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They whipt the fourth man at a poſt,</l>
                  <l>vniuſtly without fault:</l>
                  <l>And waſht his bloody body ore,</l>
                  <l>with vineger and ſalt.</l>
                  <l>And to the fifth like puniſhment,</l>
                  <l>Though to no ill he gaue conſent.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh heauen looke downe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With water they ſtuft vp the ſixth,</l>
                  <l>vntill his body ſwel'd:</l>
                  <l>The ſeuenth likewiſe with twiſted coard,</l>
                  <l>moſt barbarouſly compeld,</l>
                  <l>To ſay our Engliſh friends were thoſe,</l>
                  <l>That were the towneſmens greateſt foes.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh heauen looke downe,</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The eight with burning pincers pul'd,</l>
                  <l>made challenge of the reſt:</l>
                  <l>Though moſt vntrue, to eaſe himſelfe,</l>
                  <l>and ſo falſe things confeſt.</l>
                  <l>So did the nynth by their pretence,</l>
                  <l>Bring in moſt wrongfull euidence.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh heauen looke downe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The tenth they hung vp by the armes</l>
                  <l>two foot aboue the ground:</l>
                  <l>And ſo with ſcorching candles burn'd</l>
                  <l>his back and body round:</l>
                  <l>With all the other parts about,</l>
                  <l>Till drops of fat the lights put out.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh heauen looke downe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The reſt of theſe diſtreſſed ſoules,</l>
                  <l>were vſed in like ſort:</l>
                  <l>At which the cruell Gouernor,</l>
                  <l>made his tormenting ſport.</l>
                  <l>Till nynetéene of our Engliſhmen,</l>
                  <l>Felt more then common tortures then.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh heauen looke downe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>vpon poore innocent ſoules</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then Captaine <hi>Towerſon</hi> came in place,</l>
                  <l>to anſwer with the reſt:</l>
                  <l>To whom was told the treaſon was</l>
                  <l>by thoſe before confeſt.</l>
                  <l>Though all as falſe as God was true,</l>
                  <l>Yet they affirme, the ſame he knew.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh heauen looke downe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For which his goods were ſeized on,</l>
                  <l>which all our Engliſh had:</l>
                  <l>And ſo vnto the Iudgement ſeat,</l>
                  <l>as traitors they were led.</l>
                  <l>And there vniuſtly iudg'd to dye,</l>
                  <l>Which was performed immediately,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh heauen looke downe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ten of our men they hang'd forthwith,</l>
                  <l>the other ten went frée:</l>
                  <l>Which was a wrongfull Iudgement giuen,</l>
                  <l>and full of griefe to ſée.</l>
                  <l>That after all theſe torments paſt,</l>
                  <l>They thus ſhould ſuffer death at laſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh heauen looke downe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But on the execution day,</l>
                  <l>as God did ſo diſpoſe,</l>
                  <l>A ſudden darkeneſſe and a guſt</l>
                  <l>of violent winds aroſe.</l>
                  <l>Which caſt two of their ſhips away,</l>
                  <l>As they at road in harbour lay.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus heauen lookes downe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yea here to make Gods vengeance more,</l>
                  <l>the chiefeſt of that plot.</l>
                  <l>In this tormenting of our friends,</l>
                  <l>as then eſcaped not,</l>
                  <l>But felt Gods heauy Iron hand,</l>
                  <l>And could no way the ſame withſtand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus Heauen lookes downe &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For comming to the graues where as</l>
                  <l>the murthered bodies lay:</l>
                  <l>He fell ſtarke mad, and would not thence,</l>
                  <l>with life depart away.</l>
                  <l>But dyed moſt ſtrangely in that place,</l>
                  <l>Euen as a wretch bereft of grace:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus heauen lookes downe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus haue you heard what bloody déeds,</l>
                  <l>were late in <hi>India</hi> done:</l>
                  <l>To make vs all in <hi>England</hi> heere,</l>
                  <l>with ſorrow to thinke vpon,</l>
                  <l>What ſad misfortune ſhould be hap,</l>
                  <l>To take our friends in ſuch a trap,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet heauen lookes downe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vpon poore innocent ſoules.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_executed_men">
            <head>The names of thoſe executed.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 Captaine Gabriel Towerſon.</item>
               <item>2 Samuel Colſon Factor.</item>
               <item>3 Emanuel Tomſon Aſſiſtant.</item>
               <item>4 Timothy Iohnſon Aſſiſtant.</item>
               <item>5 Iohn Wetherall Factor.</item>
               <item>6 Iohn Clarke Aſſiſtant.</item>
               <item>7 William Griggs Factor.</item>
               <item>8 Abel Price Chyrurgian.</item>
               <item>9 Robert Browne Taylor.</item>
               <item>10 Iohn Fardo ſteward of the Engliſh houſe.</item>
               <item>As alſo nyne natiue Indians ſuffered together with them.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_pardoned_men">
            <head>The names of thoſe pardoned.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 Iohn Beomont.</item>
               <item>2 Edward Collins.</item>
               <item>3 William Webber.</item>
               <item>4 Ephraim Ramſey.</item>
               <item>5 George Sharocke.</item>
               <item>6 Iohn Sadler.</item>
               <item>7 Iohn Powell.</item>
               <item>8 Thomas Ladbrooke.</item>
               <item>9 A Portingall.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>You may read more of this bloody Tragedy in a booke printed by authory. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at London for <hi>F. Coules,</hi> dwelling at the vpper end of the Old-Baily.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
